{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "At twelve years old, this person and several others were taken captive by the Hidatsa people in a raid near modern day Washburn. When this figure rescued fallen items from a capsized boat on the Missouri River, her name was given to a tributary of the Mussellshell river. This woman, who was sold to trapper Toussaint Charbonneau [[shahr-bah-NOH]], helped guide a party through the Pacific Northwest. For ten points, name this Lemhi Shoshone [[shoh-SHOH-neh] woman who helped the Lewis and Clark expedition across the Louisiana Territory.",
      "answer": [
        "Sacagawea",
        "Sakakawea",
        "or Sacajawea"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "After this event, Musicians United for Safe Energy presented a series of nightly concerts, collectively called “No Nukes.\" When this event occurred, William Scranton III was assigned to collect and report on information about it, and PEMA declared this event an emergency with the “potential for serious radiological consequences.” Mechanical failures caused by a \"loss-of-coolant accident\" led to, for ten points, which partial meltdown at a namesake nuclear power plant in Pennsylvania?",
      "answer": "Three Mile Island accident"
    },
    {
      "question": "Fray Francisco de Aguilar records how, along with Huitlacoche [[weet-lah-KOH- cheh]], this man consumed the flesh of humans to appease his war deity. A shower of darts and stones by his countrymen led to this figure's death after his replacement by his brother, Cuitláhuac [[kweet-LAH-hwak]]. The fall of Tenochtitlan [[teh-noh-CHEET-lahn]] to Spanish forces under Hernan Cortes led to the downfall of, for ten points, which final emperor of the Aztecs?",
      "answer": [
        "Montezuma II",
        "Moctezuma II",
        "or Motecuhzomatzin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Members of this group were encouraged to see themselves as \"doctors\" for a \"national body\" suffering from \"pathogens.\" Members of this group were called \"V-Men.\" This group, targeted in Operation Carthage and the Aarhus air raid, formed the RHSA's Department Four. Klaus Barbie led this group in Lyon [[leh-OHN]] while it captured prisoners under the Night and Fog Decree. Rudolf Diels was the first head of this group, though it was led for most of World War Two by Heinrich Müller [[MYOO-ler]]. For ten points, name this Nazi secret police directed by SS chief Heinrich Himmler.",
      "answer": [
        "Gestapo",
        "Geheime Staatspolizei"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A program named for this color in Australia supposedly helped end gambling dens in Pakapoo, later ending after the passing of the Migration Act. The Vestal Virgins wore robes of this color, which nicknames a period of political repression by the Taiwanese Kuomintang from 1947 until the 1990s. Though they criticized a movement named for this color, the Black Hundreds were part of that movement with liberals and Kerenskyites in Russia. The Red Bolsheviks were opposed by a faction named for, for ten points, what color?",
      "answer": [
        "White",
        "the Whites",
        "White Terror"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In \"The Contagiousness of Puerperal Fever,\" this man correctly concluded that physicians not washing their hands was causing postpartum infections in their pregnant patients. While corresponding with William T. G. Morton, this American coined the term \"anesthesia.\" A poem by this man describes a vessel \"once red with heroes' blood,\" and contributed to the decision not to decommission the USS Constitution. The poem \"Old Ironsides\" was written by, for ten points, which fireside poet?",
      "answer": "Oliver Wendell Holmes Sr."
    },
    {
      "question": "Milton Banana supposedly created the beat central to a Samba style native to this city, which sees the Mangueira school participate in its yearly parade. Bossa Nova arose in this city, which witnessed its country's first men's football gold medal win at the Maracanã Stadium during the first Olympics ever held in South America. The 2016 Summer Olympics occurred in, for ten points, what second-most populous Brazilian city, known for its Carnival?",
      "answer": "Rio de Janeiro"
    },
    {
      "question": "Together with Shigeru Honjo, this man suppressed rebels in the February 26 Incident. This man earned the nickname \"Razor\" for his sharp mind while serving as head of the Kwantung Army. This man's speech on national radio announcing the start of one conflict ended with a rendition of \"Across the Sea.\" After the fall of Saipan, this man was forced to resign his highest office, and he was later executed for war crimes committed while in that office. For ten points, name this prime minister of Japan during most of World War Two.",
      "answer": "Hideki Tojo or Tojo Hideki"
    },
    {
      "question": "John Boehner [[BAY-ner]] attempted to draw this man into being the running mate of Bob Dole in the 1996 election, resulting in him saying, \"the possibility is too remote to comment upon, given my position.\" This man interpreted the term \"militia\" in the Second Amendment to mean \"a body of citizens\" in his majority decision in District of Columbia v. Heller. The media widely reported on this Reagan nominee's shared friendship with his left leaning colleague, Ruth Bader Ginsburg. For ten points, name this originalist and textualist U.S. Supreme Court judge who died in 2016.",
      "answer": "Antonin Scalia or Anton Gregory Scalia"
    },
    {
      "question": "Due to his father's exhausting work on calculating taxes, this scientist developed a working calculator at age nineteen, though it was primarily used as a toy for aristocrats. This man attacked casuistry [[KAZ-yoo-is-tree]] in a series of letters that were ordered to be burnt by King Louis XIV [[the Fourteenth]], and were eventually published as the Provincial Letters. Developing a notable \"Wager\" over the possibility of God's existence, for ten points, who was this French polymath of the early seventeenth century?",
      "answer": [
        "Blaise Pascal",
        "Pascal's Wager"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Under General Julio Roca, this region's indigenous population, including the Kolla and Wichi, were subordinated in the Conquest of the Desert. This region's Chubut River was the site of \"The Colony\", a venture by Welsh settlers. Puelmapu [[pwehl-MAH-poo]] is the traditional homeland of the Mapuche people, who occupy this region and the Pampas. A race of giants were rumored by explorers to live in, for ten points, what southern region of South America shared by Chile and Argentina?",
        "answer": [
          "Patagonia or Patagonian Desert",
          "Patagonian Steppe"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Patagonia forms the tip of the Southern Cone, a region consisting of South America's three wealthiest countries: Chile, Argentina, and this small country which gained independence following the 1820s Cisplatine War.",
        "answer": [
          "Uruguay",
          "Oriental Republic of Uruguay",
          "or República Oriental del Uruguay"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "General Nisbet Balfour ordered Samuel Tynes and a Loyalist militia to capture this man, resulting in the Battle of Tearcoat Swamp. This man was unable to prevent the American loss at Camden after Horatio Gates sent him on a scouting mission with the Williamsburg militia. Banastre Tarleton stated that the \"Devil himself could not catch [this officer]\" during an unsuccessful trek through 26 miles of Carolina wetlands to capture him. The \"Swamp Fox\" was the nickname given to, for ten points, which Southern Revolutionary War officer and pioneer of guerilla warfare?",
        "answer": "Francis Marion"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the French and Indian war, Francis Marion led a protracted and brutal campaign against which southern indigenous tribe, developing his techniques of irregular warfare?",
        "answer": [
          "Cherokee or Anigiduwagi",
          "Tsalagi"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An archaeologist who studied these people, Emil Forrer, suggests that their term \"Ahhiyawa\" [[ah-HEE-ywah]] refers to the Achaean [[ah-KAY-ehn]] Greeks, based on references in the 25,000 tablets found at Boğazköy [[BOHZ-koy]]. This people's prince Zannanza, who almost took the throne of Egypt, was the son of their expansionist emperor Šuppiluliuma [[soo-pih-loo-LYOO-mah]]. These people spoke the oldest known Indo- European language and fought with Ramses II at the Battle of Kadesh. For ten points, name this ancient Anatolian civilization whose final capital was Hattusa.",
        "answer": "Hittites"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Prince Zannanza died on the way to marry the widow of this pharaoh, who reversed the monotheistic reforms of his father Akhenaten.",
        "answer": [
          "Tutankhamun",
          "King Tut"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the book Results and Prospects, this man claimed that the bourgeoisie would re- assert itself if given any opportunity, formulating his theory of \"Permanent Revolution.\" After being outmaneuvered by a rival following the death of one ally, this man founded the Fourth International to oppose the Comintern. While living in exile in Mexico City, this Communist was assassinated with an ice axe by Ramón Mercader. For ten points, name this founder of the Soviet Red Army, the right-hand man of Vladimir Lenin, and rival of Joseph Stalin during the early years of the Soviet Union.",
        "answer": [
          "Leon Trotsky",
          "Lev Bronstein"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As Commissar of Foreign Affairs, Trotsky negotiated this \"shameful\" peace treaty, which pulled Russia out of World War One and ceded extensive territory to the German Empire in 1918.",
        "answer": "Treaty of Brest-Litovsk"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One side in this war was destabilized when Mariano Ignacio Prado traveled to buy armaments in Panama, willingly giving up power to his vice president, who was promptly overthrown. A five day conference on the USS Lackawanna off the port of Arica attempted to resolve this conflict. The occupation of Antofagasta began this war, and it is sometimes named for a source of fertilizer, saltpeter. Bolivia lost its coastline on the title ocean in, for ten points, which 19th century war fought by Chile and Peru?",
        "answer": [
          "War of the Pacific",
          "La Guerra del Pacifico",
          "Saltpeter War before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Some of the territory annexed by Chile lies in what driest sandy desert on Earth?",
        "answer": "Atacama Desert or Desierto de Atacama"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The conditions for the spread of this disease and a related protozoan infection were created by the establishment of sugar plantations according to J.R. McNeill's environmental history Mosquito Empires. Over five thousand people died of this disease during a 1793 outbreak in Philadelphia. William Gorgas's work in Cuba was extended by Walter Reed to treat this disease in the Panama Canal zone. For ten points, identify this tropical disease whose common name derives from the effect on skin pigment that it causes by inducing jaundice.",
        "answer": [
          "Yellow Fever",
          "Yellow Plague",
          "Yellow Jack",
          "Bronze John"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which signer of the Declaration of Independence, who served as surgeon general in the Continental Army, unsuccessfully tried to treat the Philadelphia yellow fever epidemic?",
        "answer": "Benjamin Rush"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Due to the Treaty of Tolentino, this institution housed the Statue of the Tiber River with Romulus and Remus until the Hundred Days period of 1815. The Communards set fire to the adjoining Tuileries Palace, which spread and destroyed this palace's modern-day Richelieu [[ree-shah-LOO]] wing. A former employee of this institution, Vincenzo Peruggia, successfully hid the Mona Lisa and attempted to \"return it to its homeland.\" Originally built by Philip II Augustus, for ten points, what is this French palace and museum?",
        "answer": [
          "Louvre Museum or Musée du Louvre",
          "Louvre Palace",
          "or Palais du Louvre"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Grand Louvre revitalization project was encouraged by which socialist French president of the late 20th century, the architect of the Maastricht Treaty with German chancellor Helmut Kohl?",
        "answer": "Francois Mitterand or François Marie Adrien Maurice Mitterrand"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In commemoration of a victory in the Franco-Prussian War, this composer wrote the Triumphlied [[tree-OOMF-LEED]] and dedicated it to the reigning Kaiser Wilhelm I. This composer's awarding of an honorary degree from the University of Breslau led to his rearrangement of student drinking songs in the composition Academic Festival Overture. The birth of Bertha Faber's second son inspired this composer to write his \"Wiegenlied\" [[VEE- gehn-LEED]], commonly nicknamed his \"Lullaby.\" For ten points, name this Romantic-era German composer of the Tragic Overture.",
        "answer": "Johannes Brahms"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Brahms wrote the opening notes of which Austrian Waltz King's composition, \"The Beautiful Blue Danube\"?",
        "answer": [
          "Johann Strauss II",
          "Johann Strauss the Younger",
          "or Johann Strauss the Son",
          "or Johann Strauss Jr."
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Iroquois Confederacy",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Native American Confederacy, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "U.S. state which contained the heartland of the Iroquois Confederacy's territory.",
          "answer": "New York"
        },
        {
          "question": "European colonizer and traditional ally of the Iroquois who fought alongside the Confederacy in the French and Indian War.",
          "answer": [
            "England",
            "Great Britain",
            "the United Kingdom"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Narrow, single room building which served as the primary quarters for the Iroquois.",
          "answer": "Longhouses"
        },
        {
          "question": "Animal whose pelt was traded by the League, later fighting a namesake war with the Hurons and the French for control of it.",
          "answer": [
            "Beaver",
            "Beaver War"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Eastern member of the Iroquois Confederacy which were led by Joseph Brant.",
          "answer": [
            "Mohawk",
            "Kanienʼkeháka"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "18th century British act forbidding white settlement west of the Appalachians, intending to protect the \"Indian Reserve.\"",
          "answer": "Royal Proclamation of 1763"
        },
        {
          "question": "Collective term describing the crops maize, beans, and squash, which Iroquoian society relied on.",
          "answer": "Three Sisters"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ritualistic wars fought by the Iroquois to replace members killed in battle or by disease.",
          "answer": "Mourning Wars"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Pericles",
      "prompt": "Concerning the statesman Pericles, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City-state which Pericles led at the beginning of the Peloponnesian War.",
          "answer": [
            "Athens",
            "Athenai"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Epidemic which killed Pericles, likely the same disease which caused the Black Death in medieval times.",
          "answer": [
            "Bubonic Plague",
            "either underlined portion",
            "Yersinia pestis"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Temple situated on the Acropolis whose construction was ordered by Pericles.",
          "answer": "Parthenon or Parthenónas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Historian who recorded Pericles's \"Funeral Oration\" in The History of the Peloponnesian War.",
          "answer": "Thucydides"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"League\" named for an island in the Cyclades [[sih-CLAH-dees]] which was dominated by Pericles.",
          "answer": "Delian League"
        },
        {
          "question": "Son of Miltiades [[mil-tye-AH-deez]] and victor at Salamis who was ostracized by Pericles.",
          "answer": "Cimon or Kimon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Brief war fought over an Aegean island after its philosopher-general Melissus refused to cease fighting the city of Miletus.",
          "answer": [
            "Samian War",
            "Samos War"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Lover of Pericles who Plato suggested was a brothel owner and ironically claimed that she trained many orators, including Pericles.",
          "answer": "Aspasia of Miletus"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Samurai",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Samurai, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Medieval class of European warrior with whom the samurai are often compared.",
          "answer": [
            "Knight",
            "Knighthood"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Emperor who quashed the samurai-led Satsuma Rebellion following his namesake \"Restoration.\"",
          "answer": "Emperor Meiji"
        },
        {
          "question": "Curved, single-edged sword wielded by samurai and longer than a tachi but shorter than an odachi.",
          "answer": "Katana or uchigatana"
        },
        {
          "question": "General term for the moral code followed by samurai, often equated to western chivalry.",
          "answer": "Bushido"
        },
        {
          "question": "Feudal landholders who paid a fee to retain samurai in their armed forces.",
          "answer": "Daimyo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Masterless samurai who often worked as mercenaries or bandits in feudal Japan.",
          "answer": "Ronin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Composite bow traditionally wielded by samurai most often used to face other, well armored samurai.",
          "answer": "Yumi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Specific sites where, according to tradition, samurai would try out the effectiveness of a new katana by killing random passerby.",
          "answer": [
            "Crossroads",
            "Kōsaten",
            "or Tsujigiri"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Henry Clay Work wrote a song about this event, during which hundreds drowned at Ebenezer Creek. Orlando Metcalfe Poe led engineers in this event, which succeeded the Meridian (20 pts)",
        "campaign and was governed by Special Field Order Number 120. \"Neckties\" of bent rails were created during this event, which ended with a \"Christmas Gift\" for Abraham Lincoln, the capture of (10 pts)",
        "Savannah. For ten points, name this 1864 campaign of destruction that William Tecumseh Sherman committed in Georgia, en route to the Atlantic Ocean."
      ],
      "answer": "March to the Sea or Sherman's March"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man's refusal to return José Rondeau [[rohn-DOH]] led to a period of civil war known as \"The Anarchy of the Year XX\" [[\"Twenty\"]]. This man's victory at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Maipú [[mah-ee-POOH]] is celebrated in one nation as \"Armor Day,\" and his forces were reinforced at that battle by militia under his successor, Bernardo O'Higgins. This man met fellow (10 pts)",
        "\"liberator\" Simón Bolívar at the Guayaquil [[wah-yah- KEEL]] Conference in 1822. For ten points, name this 19th century South American revolutionary who liberated Chile, Argentina, and Peru."
      ],
      "answer": "José de San Martín or José Francisco de San Martín y Matorras"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While in the King's Privy chamber, this figure gave the pseudonym John Johnson and was asked questions such as \"When and where he learned to speak French?\" This man, whose body parts were paraded around (20 pts)",
        "London after his execution, was outed by an anonymous letter which told English authorities to look for him in the Palace of Westminster. This man is burned in effigy on a namesake holiday on November (10 pts)",
        "5th. For ten points, name this English Catholic member of the Gunpowder Plot who attempted to blow up the House of Lords in 1605."
      ],
      "answer": "Guy Fawkes or Guido Fawkes"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Following a ban on these places during the American Revolution, figures such as Hugh Henry Brackenridge and William Dunlap helped revitalize them. Supporters of William Charles Macready clashed with those of Edwin Forrest during a riot at one of these places in (20 pts)",
        "Astor Place. After a man escaped from one of these places with a broken leg, Dr. Samuel Mudd assisted in harboring him. That man, whose brother Edwin worked at these places, shouted (10 pts)",
        "\"sic semper tyrannis!\" at one of them in D.C. For ten points, name this type of location where John Wilkes Booth shot Abraham Lincoln."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Theaters",
        "Playhouses"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was sent to work oversees by the publication El Espectador after he publicized government misdeeds in his work The Story of a Shipwrecked Sailor. The United Fruit Company's 1928 massacre of banana plantation (20 pts)",
        "workers in Santa Maria inspired an episode in one of this man's novels, in which the only survivor is José Arcadio Segundo, a member of the (10 pts)",
        "Buendia [[bwehn-DEE-ah]] family. The town of Macondo and its environs were inspired by, for ten points, which author's homeland of Colombia?"
      ],
      "answer": "Gabriel Garcia Marquez"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Intervention by mayor Theodore Lyman prevented this man from being tarred, feathered, and dragged through Boston Commons. This man and Benjamin Lund faced a libel suit after he reported on the barbarity of Francis (20 pts)",
        "Todd's practices in the local slave trade, resulting in the state of Maryland fining this writer. This figure formally dissolved the American Anti-Slavery Society in 1865 after declaring their mission accomplished by the passage of the 13th (10 pts)",
        "amendment. For ten points, name this abolitionist publisher of The Liberator."
      ],
      "answer": "William Lloyd Garrison"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An act of arson on this building by a slave inspired the term \"Herostratic Fame,\" in which one does a misdeed for \"fame [sought] at any cost.\" Though it was funded by a Lydian king, the poet Callimachus [[cah-leh-MAH-kus]] attributed this building to the (20 pts)",
        "Amazons. Alexander the Great offered to rebuild this wonder in the 4th century B.C. before being met with the response, \"it would be improper for one god to build a (10 pts)",
        "temple to another\" by the citizens of an Ionian city. One of the Seven Ancient Wonders, for ten points, what was this holy site in Ephesus?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Temple of Artemis or the Artemision",
        "Temple of Diana"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This politician briefly served as Secretary of Foreign Affairs as a supporter of the Party of Order. This man retired from politics in 1851 to work on an analysis of his country's society in (*) The Old Regime and the Revolution. Earlier, this man traveled to study a certain country's prison system with Gustave de Beaumont, though he developed that study into an early work of sociology that discussed the (*) Puritan roots of one nation. For ten points, name this liberal French thinker who wrote Democracy in America."
      ],
      "answer": "Alexis de Tocqueville or Alexis Charles Henri Clérel, comte de Tocqueville"
    }
  ]
}